Hello everyone. My name is Russ
Whitfield with the Alliance for Mission
and Renewal and I am excited today about
this little gathering because I have
brought two of my friends on so that we
can talk about preaching. Preaching is
one of the things that we have to do
regularly. It is so central and
important to gospel ministry. Uh and so
we want to we want to chop that up a
little bit and and our hope is that uh
no matter what your context is, no
matter what you're experiencing right
now in your own ministry, that this time
would be an encouragement to you. That
you would feel uh uplifted, affirmed,
encouraged, and maybe even gain some
creative direction for your own
preaching ministry or some some
grounding. And so, uh, with that in
mind, I want to turn it over, uh, to
Aaron Chung so he can tell you a little
about little about himself and then Paul
Kim will tell you a little bit about
himself. Fellas, let the people know who
you are. Uh, I'm Aaron, uh, married to
Hannah, uh, girl dad to Logan and
Hayden,
uh, church planter and senior pastor of
the same church, a church called Exilic,
located in Midtown Manhattan, just a few
few blocks south of Time Square. and
we're celebrating our 11year
birthday in November.
>> Snaps.
>> Awesome.
>> Snaps. Praise the Lord.
>> That's awesome. What about you, Paul?
>> Yes. Um, I'm Paul Kim. I'm in San Diego
and I'm one of the pastors at Redeemer
Presbyterian Church. Our family moved
down to San Diego in 2001. We planted it
was a church called Harbor. 10 years
later, we we merged with another church
and became Redeemer. And so, been around
since 20 almost 25 years in San Diego.
Been married to my wife, Linda. I think
it's our 27 years now. I've got three
kids and uh almost an empty neester. Uh
24 year old, 20 and 17y old.
>> That's awesome. That's awesome. Well, I
have admired and appreciate both you
brothers from afar, and I'm thankful for
your presence in our uh little ecclesial
communion. And uh before we start, my
name's Russ Whitfield. Uh I I pastored
and planted a church in Washington DC. I
have uh moved to Atlanta now to uh be a
part of another church plant called
Kindred Hope Church here in Southwest
Atlanta. I am also the assistant
coordinator for cross-cultural
advancement for Reformed University
Fellowship. So, I'm happy to be on this
with you guys today and I want to jump
right in with a question. Here's the
question. So, let's say you had a member
come up to you and they said, "Pastor,
uh, what is preaching and why is it so
important for the Christian life?" Like
they they throw you a softball. What?
How would you answer that?
>> Erin, you want to go first?
>> Um, it's it's a good question because we
only work one day a week on Sundays, so
people need to know what we do. U,
>> right.
>> Um, I mean, I I think everything starts
in Genesis 1. uh our our God is a
speaking God.
>> And whenever the idols are talked about
throughout the scriptures, they're
always known for not being able to speak
uh because they have no mouths, not
being able to hear because they have no
ears. But in Genesis 1, God is so uh
communicative
and there's there's a power actually in
his words. And so we can dive into
things like speech act theory, but when
there's a speech, a word spoken,
>> there's an action
>> that actually takes place. These words
don't fall on the dirt, but it can
literally create dirt
>> from the ground. And it has the power to
make light and the power to make humans
and and to to to bring order from
disorder. And and it's just like, you
know, when we say things like pass the
salt, like those aren't just words, but
there's an action that's created.
someone actually passes the salt to us.
And so
>> right from the beginning, we see that
our God is a a god of words
>> and whose words have power.
>> So as his sort of uh the apex of his
creation,
um we're made in his image and so we
have words and our words have power. and
preaching in particular, he's he's used
for for whatever reason, as foolish as
it is,
>> as a powerful instrument to sort of
create things like create new life,
create new
>> create uh redemption.
Um, and so we I know I know preaching
sort of has fallen our on hard times,
but I'm a firm believer that there is so
much power still in the way that we we
use our words and and way that we
preach. So in a nutshell, that's what I
would say.
>> Good, good, good, helpful. What about
you, Paul? How would you fill that in?
Yeah, I think about the prophets and
when I think about them being a
mouthpiece and thus sayeth the Lord,
>> it just reminds me of like this is a big
deal and this is God's word and it's not
about me standing in front of people
>> and trying to keep them focused and
locked in, but like we're we're
beholding God speaking to us. And for me
that that just like that just kind of
reframes my whole mentality of like this
is a holy thing to do and it's massively
humbling and
>> I guess in one sense like scary in a
good sense, right? Like this is like the
word of the Lord
>> and uh you know as I think about even
that part of it then like preaching is
not information transfer. It's not just
like I'm here to teach you stuff but
>> like for like the foolishness of the
gospel, right? like God is using like us
to be a mouthpiece to bring forth the
power of the gospel
>> and that's engaging the whole person
like the Holy Spirit can only do. So
there is this like to the heart to the
mind to the whole person and what a
dependence to say we can't do anything
we are dead and only the holy spirit
make people come alive
>> and to just think that God uses that
means that's a pretty incredible thing
to to consider and and and to reflect
on.
>> Amen. Amen. I appreciate I appreciate
those longitudinal themes in the
biblical theological approach from God
speaking in Genesis 1 moving through the
prophetic work where God chooses people
to be his mouthpieces. God wants to
reveal himself and God is most fully
revealed in Jesus Christ. And so when we
step up to preach, we're preaching
Christ all day, every day, 247.
>> You know what I'm saying? And so y
>> I appreciate that. Okay. All right.
Here's a simple one, but it may not be
so simple. So, you hear people all the
time, they might come up to you and say,
"Pastor, that was a good sermon." Or,
you know, I was listening to the radio
and I heard a good sermon. What would
y'all say are the components of a good
sermon,
man. Um,
let me kind of kick things off here.
You know, when I think about sermons and
in our preaching team and think about
when we're talking and evaluating,
there's uh there's content, there's
there's form, and there's delivery. And
I know that's kind of getting into the
rubric of things, but when I think about
content, is it like the text? Is are we
looking at the text and this is what
God's word says? And obviously, is it
going to be the
>> Jesus is the hero? It's about the gospel
of grace and highlighting and putting
the spotlight on the Jesus. I think
about that part of it all, but uh it's
also that the the the is it clear? Is it
understandable? And does it like
>> connect with people?
>> And um and then delivery. It's not just
a we're just giving a talk, but
>> like I need the Lord to go God um like
use this like help me to get out of the
way, but help like work through this in
a delivery that it's not just here to
just make sure that I'm coming across as
presentable, but like I really want
people to see Jesus and there's a
delivery aspect of it because it's
impacted the heart. I'll pause there,
but
>> I think those are that's kind of a
framework for me to think about
>> reflecting on a sermon.
>> That's helpful. Erin, what would you add
to that, brother?
>> Um yeah, no, I I definitely agree with
that. And just to piggy back off of what
Paul said, I think um the clarity part
is really important. So,
>> a few rubrics that have helped me is um
what what do the people need to know?
>> Why do they need to know it? Yeah,
>> because if they don't, there's no reason
to listen to you, then there's no reason
to listen to you. So, what do they know?
Why do they need to know it? What do
they need to do?
>> Why do they need to do it? Those are
some helpful frameworks for uh clarity
in a sermon. Um I think I think also
another big thing is I think you know
chances are if you're listening to this
video or watching it, you're you're um
influenced by uh the reformed faith and
and that kind of crystal preaching. And
so typically if you've been influenced
by people like Clowny and Keller, you're
probably good at like, you know,
redemptive historical preaching,
crystalentric preaching, you know, to
put Jesus somewhere in the sermon and
and all that. I I think the one area
we're not as good at though is um
>> uh communicating to skeptics,
>> cultural engagement, u reaching reaching
the lost. I don't think we're good at
that. And I think when you when you look
at scripture and when Jesus is teaching
and preaching in particular, he would
often say things like you have heard
that it was said, but I say to you,
>> there's some kind of cultural exit Jesus
that he's doing there.
>> Uh he's talking about how the people
have been formed whether by philosophy
or by the city of Rome, commerce, etc.
uh but he's challenging them with sort
of a counter katakizes
>> or the cultural zeitgeist of the moment.
And so a lot of my preaching I spent
probably the bulk of that on cultural
exit Jesus cuz when you've been
preaching enough and you have all these
helpful frameworks um the redemptive
historical crystal part gets easier and
easier. uh you you still have to be lost
in wonder as you're talking about that
stuff obviously but you also have to do
a lot of hard work in terms of as Keller
would say when I when I preach I have
the Bible in one hand the New York Times
on the other and so it doesn't have to
be the New York Times it could be Tik
Tok it could be something else but there
has to be some kind of some kind of
cultural engagement that is going on to
your specific local
>> yeah that's good I appreciate those
answers I I I I I I hear y'all saying,
but essentially preaching is is about
preaching the good news into the daily
news so that people
>> are able to live into the the message of
the person and work of Christ in the
times that they have before them.
>> Uh and I find that really helpful and
clarifying.
>> Great. Let's talk a little bit about the
work of preaching because you know we
all we went to seminary. Um most many of
us uh have gone to seminary prior to
getting into pastoral ministry and in
seminary they give you preaching courses
and you you learn some of the mechanics
of preaching. But after some time you
begin to personalize that. You begin to
figure out what works for you, what's
helpful for you, what's not quite so
helpful. that's often integrated with
the type of people you're pastoring in
the particular mission of your place.
Uh, and so my question to y'all is how
do you approach your sermon prep every
week? What what goes into it? How would
you give us the kind of playbyplay?
>> Paul, I I I kind of want to hear from
you first because you've been doing it
longer.
>> All right. Um,
yeah, that's a great question. I think
first when we do a series like we're
doing the Gospel of Mark right now about
over a year and a half there's a lot of
prep work just to kind of frame
everything get into the just kind of
look at the passage and understand it
and study it on a meta big level
>> and once we kind of map it out in terms
of our calendar we're going through that
I guess to get granular to like what
does a sermon prep look like for me um I
think it's at least in this season of
time where uh I've been in 25 plus years
of ministry
I would say that the bulk of my prep
work is Wednesdays and Thursdays and uh
Mondays and Tuesdays we have a lot of
church meetings, but I'm looking at the
text Monday and Tuesday and I'm just
reading and I'm thinking I'm reflecting
and that's all I'm doing.
>> And then by Wednesday, my goal is I'm
praying and studying it saying, is there
a framework? Is there like like kind of
what what Erin said like what why does
this matter? What's it saying? Why is
this significant? and can I be able to
like get it from God's word to like be
able to articulate it and then fill out
that framework
>> so that kind of my goal is by Wednesday
if I was just to put it out there and
like I had nothing else to do it there
would be something there ready to go to
communicate
>> Thursday then for me is just praying it
through fleshing it out looking at
commentaries uh just kind of reflecting
mulling it over and then uh for us the
slides are due by the um by the end into
that day. I take Fridays off, Saturdays
off, Saturday night, I'm I'm I'm going
back into it. Sunday morning, I'm
praying.
>> So, that's that's kind of the format for
me. I'm at a place right now where it's
um
>> I'm not using notes. So, it's just
settling in my heart and my brain like
through that process.
That being said, I think if I could just
summarize that Mondays and Tuesdays and
leading up to Wednesday, it's the I want
to be able to like sit and listen to
what God's word has to say versus like I
need to like like Lord, what is this
word saying and what, you know, and and
just come underneath that and then let
that frame get to a place of then
unpacking, you know. So,
>> that's helpful. That's helpful. What
about you, Aaron?
>> Uh, quick quick question for Paul. Just
you're one of the few guys I know that
doesn't use any notes at all. Do you
actually like rehearse it? And if so,
how many times before you feel
comfortable enough to jump up there?
>> Yeah, that's a great question. I I don't
technically rehearse it anymore like in
terms of practicing going through it. I
think what I what let me reframe that.
while I'm doing the prep, I'm thinking
about it so much so that the the text
and the main point, I can kind of
reflect on it and then since I'm just
going over it over again, by the time I
get to Sunday, it's pretty much like
pressed into my mind and my heart. Let
me give you a quick example. Like this
past Sunday was we're going through the
Gospel of Mark and it's the Syrian
woman. So just that text, you know, it's
like that weird saying of Jesus like,
"Are you offensive? like what what are
you doing? And part of like Monday and
Tuesday was just thinking and saying God
this is a text like what God help me I
need you. But what are you trying to
like help me to understand your word is
saying and it just kind of through that
process framed like asking the main
question like why people would would
care about this like why is this even in
the passage and just kind of frame the
introduction because that's a question
that people are asking and then through
that part um to say to grab our
attention to in order to highlight a
remarkable faith from someone that
nobody would have expected. So for me
that was like working through to get to
that statement was through resting it
unpacking it. By the time then by
Wednesday, Thursday, I'm just unpacking
that going to like how does that for
Jesus? How does that apply that? So that
when Sunday comes, I already know that
like from reflecting on that kind of
like this is the main key thing from the
text and I could just unpack it and go
from there.
>> That helps.
>> Yeah. And then just for myself and all
our listeners, I it might be hard, but
how much how many hours do you think you
put into that sermon? Even even like the
chewing meditating part like how many
hours come out to a week?
>> That's a great question. I I don't know
if I really actually like specifically
thought through it, but I probably
um
Mondays and Tuesdays are just a couple
hours because I was meditating. Think
about it. Wednesdays and Thursdays, it's
the bulk is in the morning times because
I, you know, I think the best and I'm
more focused in the morning times. So
Wednesdays and Thursdays I'm really
locked into there and then Saturday and
Sunday I'm like in Sunday I'm just like
praying
>> um
>> 12 to 15 hours maybe uh now I think it
was it was more beforehand but I I just
say that and I I this is challenging me
to maybe look at it more carefully but I
would say something like that.
>> It's it sounds like it's at least 15 if
not more. um the in even just in terms
of the prayer part and preparation part
cuz I
>> I think I was thinking about my my own
it's hard for me to get too but I I
think I'm like I might be 20 plus
>> and so a part of that is um
>> I think for me I'm working at I'm
probably working on three sermons at
once and a part of that is because uh it
kind of bleeds into my study time. I'm
just I'm just consuming as much as I can
and um and sometimes when I'm consuming
as as much as I can, I find something
good, I'll archive it for a future
sermon down the line. So the it's hard,
at least personally for me, I'm I'm
rarely working on one sermon at once
just because I need input to do output
and um I'm not smart enough just to have
all this input in my mind. I I need I
just need to consume like constantly to
be able to do any output. Um and so and
then to your point just meditating
uh on the passage and um
and it lighting a fire in my bosom
before I speak it is is really key. Um
there was a I forget I think it was
Whitfield. Someone came out to Whitfield
once and was like, "I don't believe in
what you're saying, but you make me want
to believe it because you believe in it
so much." And so, just
>> Thanks, Aaron. I appreciate that, man.
>> I feel like when most of us get up there
on the pulpit, it's just like,
>> I don't believe in what you're saying,
and you don't really make me want to
believe in it either, you know? And so
how can it like penetrate into my heart
so much that even those that might
disagree with me
>> they see a man that believes in this
thing so much that there's something
very u tantalizing about it
>> and so just emotionally getting to the
place where you're able to do that every
it's not easy so there's anoint that's
there
>> that's that's good Erin I you know in
light of what you shared it just made me
think you know part of it for me is like
the when I said like 12 to 15 and maybe
that's specifically on the message and
where I for myself part of that like
like always reading I I'll pro I spend
probably a like a good hour a day in the
morning time just to read and it's not
to read for the sermon prep but just
reading
>> right
>> and I think that's part so if I were to
include all those different parts but I
don't really do it that way more it's
more like I want to learn and grow and
that's what I would say to probably my
25-year-old version one of the things I
would say is like play the long
and like it'll play like you trust that
it'll give you dividends in the sense of
like you're learning, you're processing,
you're thinking, and you're growing over
time. And then I think part of it now at
times is when I'm reflecting I'm like,
"Oh, I remember that." And it's it's not
like I'm taking a lot of notes even when
I'm reading. But for some, I guess in
terms of how I'm wired, I think about
certain things and it just some of it
just sticks and then it'll kind of come
back to it again and again. So that's
kind of my approach right now in this
season of like I'm doing this constant
like I want to learn, I want to listen,
I want to reflect on it and then there's
the text in general. And for me right
now it's like um you know like the
studying part but like I just want to be
like this to like I want to hear and
like have the Holy Spirit give the word
to me. So then then then it's presented
to you know to the congregation.
And Paul, when you find something good
that's not relevant to the this week's
sermon, do you archive it somewhere? Do
you have like some kind of dock where
it's like future sermon or like, you
know, is is there a way you do?
>> I, you know, I wish I was like more
organized to do that. I I I I really
don't. And I think that's I just kind of
remember and I'll keep it. Sometimes
I'll write something down, but I don't
have a very organized file. Um, and I'm
not saying that of course, like I
probably do need to. that probably will
make me grow even more and maybe that's
one of my growth things I need to do.
Yeah.
>> All right. So, we talked a little bit
about some of the mechanics and the work
of preaching the everyday stuff. Let's
get into some of the contextual
challenges. Um,
what is it? How do y'all think about
engaging skeptical people or uninitiated
people from the pulpit? Because we are
charged with equipping the saints for
the work of ministry. We are charged
with, you know, exhorting the saints,
cultivating them, disciplehip,
formation, like there's a pretty
holistic picture about our
responsibilities toward God's people as
pastors. Uh, but we are also very clear
from scripture that that we have a a
call as missionaries and our work of
evangelism is is crucial to our
ministry. And so when you when you think
about getting up in the pulpit and
having to not only speak to God's
people, but also try to speak to our our
neighbors who show up on a, you know,
across a spectrum of different beliefs
and experiences with respect to faith.
How do y'all think about that challenge
and in preaching in such a way where it
it can speak to to the different groups?
>> Erin, why don't you go with this one,
brother? Yeah, I the the one thing that
I think about often is what Keller used
to say when when the reason for God came
out. Um there were a lot of Christians
that were reading The Reason for God. Um
but I think I think Tim would say that
the book was really reaching mostly the
Christian audience to a certain degree.
Um and so later on he wrote Making Sense
of God, uh which he considered more of a
prequel to Reason for God. And those
topics were very different than the
topics that were written in the reason
for god. So the reason for god the
topics are things like things like
science and why is Christianity so uh
exclusive and not inclusive and isn't it
a moral street jacket and things like
that. the making sense of God. The
topics were things on identity, meaning,
hope, freedom, like these topics were
very different compared to the reasons
for God. And I I think if you're going
to reach our culture today, you have to
hit those topics. almost every sermon
has to hit either
>> identity formation, what freedom really
is,
um, uh, issues of hope because we're
we're hope based creatures. Um, and so
it has to hit more of that kind of stuff
than just the the the the stuff that we
kind of like Christians are interested
in. And so I make it a point to almost
include some like one category from them
from making sense of God in every single
sermon I do.
>> Um and so that's way I I try to and I I
just assume that no one in our church is
a Christian to a certain degree. And
that also helps me frame how I'm
communicating and and we've seen
actually a good amount of fruit with
skeptics coming to our church and and
coming to faith. So
>> yeah,
>> Paul, what about you? Yeah, I would say
for people listening in and for
preachers
why
spending time really then with
non-Christians and struggling Christians
or people who are not sure are is really
important
that helps me a lot to kind of hear what
they're going through. And then I'm
thinking about my Southern California,
San Diego context. So for me that is
such a helpful way to kind of
personalize it and engage and as I'm
listening to them it helps me when I'm
when I'm preparing to serve in to go
what's the question that that everyone's
asking but even like these people that
I'm actually like would face is like
what would they think about this like
what struggle would they have or what
what what push back would they have and
that that would be so significant for
me. So, in terms of like engaging
people,
I like uh I just spent five weeks going
through a Gospel of Mark investigative
study with a couple. It's so helpful for
them to like just for me to listen and
process with them and they're being very
honest when they go through this reading
and they're like, I have a problem with
this hell thing. Just kind of listening
and going, okay, what's going on here?
And it helps me then to think about the
questions that they have in particular.
And that's been really significant. So,
I would just say would encourage that.
We want to always have that on. And I
would say it's not only non-Christians,
but um you know who's really good is
teenagers because they're in that world
and you I would even talk to my my kids
about it or even like they've got
non-Christian friends and just kind of
get a pulse between like what's going on
like what would be like what issues they
would have. That's been helpful for me
just as trying to be a student of not
only our culture in terms of the the
like all the amazing things that Erin's
saying. I'm like yes and amen. but to
personalize it and to know what San
Diego and like the people here are going
through and then addressing the gospel
and not just their beliefs but I think
also maybe my my sense not like they're
like this whole sense of like their own
experiential like something's missing
and just kind of getting that part to
the gospel you know as well.
All right. It's another but related
question is is what do you think when
you look out over your place now? We
recognize that there there there's a lot
of cultural dynamism in our country. You
you got subcultures, you got a
prevailing American culture, you got
urban culture, you got rural culture,
suburban culture. It cultures
everywhere. Uh, and so it's it's not
necessarily the same for all of us how
we would answer this question, but what
do what do you find to be the most
challenging dynamics of preaching into
our cultural moment and why?
I I'm pretty I'm so curious and my sense
is uh there's you know there's the
geographical unique part and the where
our churches are that's probably going
to factor in and obviously uh for those
of United States there's a unique
dynamic of that and who our people are
too. This is going to come to no
surprise, but in San Diego, the the the
the idol of comfort and a good life and
like being committed to Jesus and
saying, "I'm going to follow him. It's
going to it's worth the sacrifice to
deny the cross, you know, deny I mean,
deny myself, carry the cross, and follow
me." That's like the like that is such a
significant
narrative to um
speaking to Christians and
non-Christians. Like why in the world
would I want to commit to uh to
following Jesus that's going to cause me
to sacrifice in this way? So that's part
at least for for us in San Diego the
main kind of storyline of idolatry that
comes across maybe more than anything
else. I'll pause there and I know we
could talk so much more about different
stuff but want to let you know Aaron
share and I'm sure I'm curious it's
probably going to be different similar
but maybe different. Yeah, I mean I I do
think in general there's been a
flattening out of our shared collective
experiences just because of the internet
and social media. So it's not as though
like New York and San Diego are light
years ahead of
>> rural countryside anymore. Uh having
said that there are still a lot of
differences. I was just in Montana last
week for a few days and the nomenclature
and ethos of Montana is obviously really
different than New York City and so
there's still differences with the local
that we live in and and Russ you know
this I mean being from New York I mean
we even when we're not in a hurry we're
in a hurry and uh we're walking fast for
no reason and so uh as Comr would say
the ruthless elimination of hurry is is
going to perpetually be a challenge I
think for New Yorkers just slowing down
to Sabbath and be with God to breathe.
Breathing I think is even hard. Um
>> that will perpetually be a challenge. I
think community life will constantly be
a challenge just cuz people are in and
out, in and out. I think a sense of
fatalism, the way that we view people,
just cuz we're surrounded by people all
the time. And our our our level of
compassion when we see someone that
might be homeless can sort of dissipate
just cuz we see it all the time. I mean,
there's a a bad cynicism sometimes with
um New Yorkers that's there. Um and so,
uh still viewing people through the eyes
of God is is going to be really
important. Um and money obviously is is
really big here. And so fighting to have
a biblical understanding of money and
ambition uh and faith and work is is
still really big here.
>> Yeah. I the I would maybe that one thing
that I've maybe I'm taking note of
especially with the college students in
the 20s
what I'm noticing is because of you know
this thing they're um the deeper level
of anxiety
>> of
just being insular and uh feeling so
insecure.
I think that's such a a common
theme that I'm uh that I'm seeing. And
what does it mean then for the gospel to
address that in a way that it creates
not only the challenge but the longing
of how Jesus is better? But I I I I you
know, I'm still as a as a as a student
learner, I'm trying to think through
like what are the gospel implications
for that where it's like the gospel
brings you something so much more
beautiful and lasting addressing that.
But the gospel also just engages you to
like the challenge like there's
something like of this like again going
into the comfort here of like what does
it mean to get yourself out of it and
the I think the screen has made people
made people more self-absorbed in in
coverture they say like more inward than
ever before. So even when it comes to
like there's awkwardness of dating and
relationship they're thinking about
themselves you know you know all of this
stuff. So to have a healthy gospel
identity, but that's a common theme that
that just seems to be I'm hearing it
over and over again here in San Diego.
>> Okay. Okay. So, um I want to I want to
shift just a little bit. Uh and I want I
want to ask a fun question and then I
want to continue to roll through. So
here's my fun question. What is what's
one of your most memorable preaching
experiences in the wild? So what what do
I mean by that? I mean a preaching
situation where it wasn't a Sunday
morning to your people. It might have
been a civic leader who asked you to
come and offer a brief word in the
context of a community meeting or you
know the local uh sports team asked you
to come and do something like what is
what's one one of your most memorable uh
experiences preaching in the wild and
why?
Aaron, you want to go first?
>> Ah, man. I
I I don't know if it's considered in the
wild, but I um something happened to me
that most pastors would never want to
happen to them. So, I was guest speaking
at my friend's church. And so, you know,
like you want to do a good job cuz you
know, you're you're you're guest
speaking for your friend's church. And
so I get up there and I I open my iPad
and I I open my doc and it says loading.
Oh no.
So I got up there and I was panicking.
And so I literally preached that like
unlike Paul, I can't preach without
notes and I wasn't super comfortable
with the sermon to begin with. And so I
literally preached the whole thing
without any notes at all. And that that
sermon was not my finest moment. And so
that was Yeah.
>> funny at the same time.
>> That's funny. What about you, Paul?
>> Oh man. Um
during sbatical,
you know, we were visiting several
churches here. And when I say this is
like in the wild, it was probably the
one that got me out of my most like
biggest comfort zone, but it was also
one of the most amazing experiences too
where I humbled learning, processing so
much stuff. So, uh, we visited this
black church in San Diego and wow, it
was amazing. And yet when I when I when
Lynn and I walked in, they embraced us.
And the pastor there, first of all, he's
like like a jiu-jitsu master, too. Like
I mean he's like just this big guy who
is like intimidating and scary and like
but like presence. So I'm like I'm on
sabatical pastor here in San Diego. He's
like well come on up. We're going to
have you sit up here. I'm like oh no no
I'm not. He's like yes you are.
>> And so I am dressed like this like San
Diego clothes. They're in suits. Uh they
have a pulpit. There's like chairs in
the back. And I'm sitting there and then
my wife is sitting with the pastor's
wife and we're I'm just like, "Wow."
Okay. And then he's like, "And Pastor
Paul's here. He's going to give us a
word right now on something." And I was
like, "Oh my gosh, what am I going to
say?" So I don't I don't recall exactly
what I said, but I did say, "Hey, we're
on sbatical." And it was like in July,
so my wife and I were celebrating um our
anniversary. It's you know, our birthday
is the anniversary of July. So we did
that. people are responsive. It was
amazing. And then after that, like right
after that, he he he has my wife come up
with me and says, "We're gonna sing
happy birthday to them." And I'm just
like, "Oh my gosh." Like I was just so
out of it was so community and
beautiful. And uh I thought that was for
me. And then when you know I'm still
like it was a long service and I'm
sitting in the back and he's preaching
and I'm just amazed by the giftedness of
this preacher,
>> the the the passion, the authority, the
um the the power of God's word and to be
able to just kind of like be there while
I'm sitting like this saying, "What am I
doing here? Why am I up here?" And to
engage that. So it's not like me
particularly preaching per se, but that
experience was incredible. And I will
say this, I still listen to his sermons
>> if I were to be like one of the people
because I just am like, "Wow, that is it
pushes me in a way that um not my what
I'm used to, but also it has grown me
too." So
>> nice. Nice. All right, y'all. So uh I so
I asked this question because you know
different listeners are going to be at
different stages in their development in
ministry especially if they're in
pastoral ministry or heading toward
pastoral ministry and one of I think
it's an occupational hazard as it
relates to pastoral ministry is that
younger people in seminary will often
compare themselves to preachers and
pastors who have been doing it longer
than they've been alive and often times
that will not have the function of
encouraging them and and giving them
something to aspire to. It'll make them
feel like they don't measure up and
they're and they couldn't possibly
become good preachers. But we know uh
that it takes time to actually find your
preaching voice, to actually know who
you are, who you're not, to be
comfortable in your own skin, and to
know the voice that God has given you
based upon your experiences, your own
life in Christ, and your own, you know,
training and ministry and family and
story. So my question to y'all is like,
how long did it take you to find your
preaching voice? Like how long did it
take you? Uh, you can go how many
sermons, reps, you can go how many years
of preaching, but h how long did it take
you to find your own preaching voice to
where you knew who you are and you don't
feel like you have to index your
preaching to some other great preacher?
>> Yeah.
>> Um, man, that that's a hard question for
me to answer because I feel like I'm
still finding it. Um, I I feel like my
my preaching continues to evolve and I
suspect that it will continue to evolve
even 10 years from now. Um, I think I
think early on a lot of us tried to do a
bad impersonation of Keller or a
favorite preacher. Um, there does come a
point though where you you realize that
God has hardwired you and made you very
unique and that's something that you
should honor. And when you honor that
authenticity of how God made you, the
sermons actually tend to land a lot
better, uh, because
>> the people are are are really seeing
you, you know, versus a a version of
someone else that's not as good. Um, so
I Yeah, I
I feel like I'm I'm continually finding
it. I I interestingly enough, I probably
listen to more non-reform preachers now.
uh than reformed preachers. Uh mostly
again because of the um the redemptive
historical crystal park. It's it's a
little bit easier than before. That part
gets easier. I think it's more just um
communicating well clarity
uh relevance um all that stuff is really
important and
um so in some ways I feel like my my
preaching is continually evolving to be
honest.
>> No, that's fair. That's fair. What about
you Paul?
Yeah, I think first in thinking about
that question and people are listening
to this. I don't think it's so much
we're not trying to say it's after a
certain like maybe like just even time
or space first. I do think reps and you
know getting more comfortable your voice
does matter. So I let me say that. But I
think part of getting to that is taking
a step back and going like what am I
wanting and longing for and what kind of
person am I trying to be or become? And
you know as preachers it's so tied to
our identity.
>> So I don't think this is something that
we're ever going to like you know be
freed of. It's going to be a struggle
for for all of us who are pastors. But
to consistently go Lord like you delight
in me and who am I? What's my story? And
how how are how how have you made me to
be who I am?
>> And how can I honor you with then the
way that you have wired me, my
personality, and and how can I continue
to cultivate and grow that? I would be
ask I would be encouraging people
whether younger, older, at any age and
stage of of preaching and ministry to
just kind of to reflect and pray and get
the gospel into your heart. And as that
begins to happen, I just think, you
know, the process of the Holy Spirit
working begins to settle you. So you're
just like, "Okay, Lord, um you delight
in me. It's not being found in this
person or that person or I need to show
up and and do that." So I I would just
encourage people like because that's
what I need to do even now from like my
10 year, you know, Paul came from 10
years ago, 20 years ago, and so forth.
That being said, I think there are there
does come some time as you do ministry.
Um I don't know maybe the felt
experiences like I kind of go h gosh
like uh I
I'm this is just for me my experience
like instead of just trying to get
information and just saying oh that
person that's really cool what's doing
that I kind of go like Lord I want to
like Lord uh I want your word to go
deeper in me and like like let that form
and shape and then let that like let's
that that becomes more of a like Jesus
just do something in my own heart to go
deeper. That's how it came for me. And I
think that maybe happened about after 10
years of ministry. I felt like yes, I
was listening to Keller. I was Spurgeon
and all these different people and you
know you you name it. And it came to a
point of saying Lord I'm hungry for like
like help me to drink from the water.
And uh other people are telling me how
to drink. They're they're telling I'm
learning from what they're drinking from
the water. I want to be able to do that.
And so it is that over time that
happened. And I think more and more as
I'm in ministry and now I'm I'm I'm 51.
I don't know maybe it's more like the
past 5 years or so just coming to a
place of settleness to go okay Lord I
want to cons I want to continually grow
as a as a preacher as a way to honor you
but
this is who I am. Help me to cultivate
this. So like there. So I would say that
that's that's my testimony I would say
and maybe that's helpful. So those are
some of the things in terms of just how
I would respond to that question.
>> Yeah. Thank y'all. Um so here's a here's
a question. Um,
as you think back on the preacher that
you were and and you consider the
preacher that you are and and you know
all of the lessons that you've learned,
all of the hard-fought wisdom that
you've acquired over the years, when you
think about where you were as it related
to your thinking about preaching or the,
you know, your approach to preaching,
anything related to that
>> and you compare that to where you are
now, if you could go back to your
25year-old self, or your your
23-year-old self and give them some
advice about preaching. What would you
be most urgently trying to impress upon
your younger self?
I think for me
now I would say again this is this is
kind of Paul Kim right everyone's
different in in in their story and their
in their learning I would say less is
more
>> and it's not just especially the
reformed camps like you're not here just
to like let every single detail like
what you learn kind of needs to come out
but like less is more and there's wisdom
to that
>> um
>> I would say
It's not all about passion.
>> I used to think like
this like like passion that people are
going to listen to you. They you can
like what does it mean like
that you are speaking to people in a way
and discerning the spirit of God and not
like you know like one decel level high
versus and again just kind of getting
into the deliveries but it's not just
like I'm not trying to just be like a
formula to go up and down and doing all
that but it's not like I felt like
before it was like you know like yeah
she like I almost I want to shove the
gospel down your throat like show you
how how amazing this is and it is but I
think I to take a step back and go at
least for me um it's not just about that
part to it. So those are maybe two
things for me and then I would say play
the long game like lead grow process and
uh and and then we as we talked about um
learn to see like God delights in you
>> and find your voice.
Find your voice.
>> That's good. What about you, Aaron?
>> Yeah, so I see a counselor and um he's a
retired Anglican bishop and um I think I
think the feeling that I always have
with him after a counseling session was
oh he was with the Lord like he he just
came down from Sinai
>> and like I could feel the presence of
God around him. there's like a glory
cloud hovering over him.
And I think this is why like when um
especially if you're younger, we we get
up and our and our content is like the
same as like a Keller or someone else,
but it doesn't land the same way. And
you're like, but I'm saying the exact
same thing. Like why isn't hitting
everyone and why don't I have a mega
church? And a part of it is cuz he was
with the Lord,
you know, like his presence like that's
why there's a the weight feels
different. You're saying the same
things, but the weight is different. And
a part of it is cuz he was with the
Lord. And so
>> I think that just being near his fiery
presence is is as important as being
near your commentaries.
Uh, I think it's one thing if our job
was just to be a brick layer, like you
don't need to be near the presence of
the Lord or emotionally healthy to lay
bricks. You just lay bricks and you just
it's a physical endeavor. But with us,
there's like so much of a spiritual
warfare
that's involved. Like there's a good
chance you might fight with your wife on
Saturday night, you know, and then you
got to preach on Sunday morning and like
you're like you have to be in a healthy
place. And so a lot of that is that kind
of hard work is really important. Um,
but just being near his presence is
really important. I think that's why I
think as you get older, I mean, Lloyd
Jones once said, "Don't let the pulpit
drive you to the word, but let the word
drive you to the pulpit." And I think
when you're younger, it's like the
pulpit is driving you to the word
because it's like, "Oh, I got to preach
again. It's Sunday coming. Sunday
coming." Or like we're kind of using our
devotionals as like fodder for the
sermon. And like everything is driving
us like the pulpit is driving us to the
word rather than the word driving us to
the pulpit. But hopefully when you get
up there on Sunday morning or whenever
you have service like there's something
about like the fire of God's word that
is like
um exuding out of you when you get get
up there.
>> Uh which is why you want to get up
there. So being near his presence is
actually pretty big.
Yeah, that's that's good. Aaron, there's
a phrase I again this is I don't
remember who said it, but as you were
talking, Aaron said crucified preaching
comes from a crucified preacher,
>> right?
>> And um
>> you know, learning to die to self and
like the gospel and like being with the
Lord and Jesus and what that means,
right? That um good word, good reminder.
>> Yeah. So um Okay. What do you guys do
after you preach? What like how do you
replenish or recover or re restore your
soul after you pour it out on a Sunday
morning? Right? Because it's it's Sunday
morning is the culmination of lots of
hours of work through the week and then
Sunday's coming again. So, how do you
preachers keep yourselves
rooted and rested? What do you do right
after preaching? What's your what's your
rhythm?
>> Um, one helpful advice for me was um
if you like Sabbathing wise, so if you
work with your hands, like you're a
construction worker or you're an artist
or whatever, if you work with your
hands, Sabbath with your mind. But if
you work with your mind, which is most
preachers, Sabbath with your hands. And
so one way that I sabbath with my hands
is uh we do family workouts. So
including our two kids and and so we do
a lot of that together. Um I try to play
basketball on Sunday nights with some
dads.
Um
I like a good cigar and drink. Um I love
just catching up with my wife for the
week ahead. syncing our calendars and
um and just laughing together has been
really good. Um I think hanging out with
other pastors on a Sunday night or
Monday night sometimes um is really cool
too. Just
>> talking about our our our battle scars
and things like that and and just the
collegiality of of a community like that
is really good too. So you know you're
not alone. So those are some things.
>> Yeah.
>> What about you, Paul?
I just want to sleep. So, a holy nap,
right? I I think that's like and and I'm
thankful for that. And it also shows my
idols when I'm like, dude, I can't take
a nap. I have to do this. I get all like
irritated and like I deserve this, you
know? Um,
no, but for all I think it's such a
moment where your adrenaline is moving,
you're depending on the spirit of God.
you're on, you know, you're engaged.
You're like, "This is incredible." I,
you know, it's also humbling. You're
like, "Did it do anything? I feel like,
you know, you're just, there's so many
things going on that you that I would be
feeling um, you know, after the services
are done and to just kind of go and one
thing I don't do is um, you know, ask my
wife, so um, what you think?" Uh, I'm
not ready for that. She knows like I
mean
>> only if you're like saying that was a
revival sermon, the best one I ever
heard. Okay, that yeah, sure. You know,
kids say that, but you know, I'm I'm all
joking aside, like
>> I know that I could become like since
I'm tired and spent,
>> I I have to really guard my heart
>> and uh and then my since my wife is
there and especially because we're
interacting and talking, I just like,
hey, h I probably just need some time
and you know, in processing this, this
is just for me and I just need to take a
step back, recharge. And the way that I
need to recharge that is is to take a
nap, to just kind of go for a walk and
just to kind of get that into a place of
of settleness. So nothing wild and
crazy, but like those are some things
that are helpful. And I know I'm not
ready to hear some feedback right
afterwards unless it's amazing, but then
no, that's going to feed it to my
approval idol. So yeah.
>> Well, thank you. Well, I I only have one
question left to to land the plane, but
I want to thank you both for giving your
time to to share a little bit about your
own journey and your own thinking around
preaching. Uh I'm I'm I'm sure that the
Lord is going to use something of what
has been said today to encourage others
and bless others. But for my final
question, I just want to ask like what
what would your counsel or encouragement
be to your fellow preachers out there
before we wrap this thing? you know how
people are coming in. Some people, it
doesn't matter. Some people have only
been preaching for for a short time.
Some of the people out there have been
preaching longer than all three of us.
Uh some people are in the middle of a
lot of church drama. Uh they're facing a
lot of hard times, suffering. Maybe the
budget of the church is struggling or
their community is facing uh grief.
There are there are just so many
different dynamics that could be at work
in the lives and ministries of those who
are listening here. So given the rough
terrain in which we are called to do
ministry, what would be your final
encouragements to to your fellow
preachers out there who are listening?
>> I mean I would just encourage and go in
the gospel be faithful.
God uh can you know can speak through a
donkey and and bring about power and
change and the outcome is going to be
the Lord's. So take heart in that
>> and I would just also just you know
along with the encouragement like let's
remember that your identity is not found
in preaching and I know we'll all nod
our heads to that
>> but our hearts have to get to that point
of saying that and giving that to Jesus
and there's a form of dying
>> to to doing that. So, um I think it's so
significant and and even this
conversation highlights what an
incredible privilege it is, but at the
same time, let's not make it the idol of
making it more than it is. And I think
part of even the posture of preaching is
a relationship with God that's honest
sometimes for me just to go, Lord, I I I
am tired. I I don't feel like I got much
like you you you need to show up. and or
other places of just like Lord, I'm just
frustrated. I have so much to do. So,
just like just constantly just getting
into that place of having my heart uh be
honest and vulnerable with my savior as
I'm articulating and thinking about the
sermon that's coming up and just
processing that and the weight behind
like all that is there and to making
myself remember I'm not the Lord.
>> Amen. Amen. Ear.
>> Yeah. I I would say
I would say Jesus loves the local
church. And so there's a lot of great
preachers online.
Um and they might be better preachers,
but they're not better shepherds. And so
if you're a pastor of a local church,
you know your people the best. And God
has placed you there for a reason to
minister to the pains and wounds of your
people that people online cannot do.
>> And so um be faithful in that.
um the everyone online can do what they
do, but Jesus has placed you there to be
the shepherd of your people. And that's
what your people actually need the most.
>> And so, um so I would just tell uh you
know, our fellow pastors in these
positions just to just to persevere, to
be faithful, to not compare
uh and just to have a heart for your
particular people.
>> Amen. Amen. Well, again, thank you both
for giving of your time to to have a
little conversation about preaching. And
thank you to all of you who have uh
who've tuned in to the AMR uh website to
check out this video. Uh we hope that
the Lord uh will encourage your heart by
what you've heard today, that he will
bless you in your ministry, that he will
keep you dependent and relying upon him,
and that through you he'll produce much
fruit. So, the Lord bless you all. uh
and uh we hope that uh the AMR uh would
encourage you uh in the coming weeks,
months, and years uh in in your
ministry.
>> Can I just close by saying, man, uh
Russ, thanks for so much for hosting.
>> Yeah,
>> I think there needs to be another one
where I want to hear from you, brother,
and hear from your lens because interest
because I I I honestly do and so uh hope
that can happen and this will be a, you
know, TBD to be continued type of thing.
So, thanks for hosting, brother. Thank
you so much for that. We might have to
do a part two, y'all. But until then,
the Lord bless you. Be well.